Hi, there my name is justin touching
...a senior program manager on the operating systems group today I'm here to talk to-you about
apps and devices that print...windows ten and windows ten mobile.
A brief overview of what I'll do today I'll give you an overview of architecture
in windows ten I'll tell you about how design apps that print and then for...that
happen to be tuning in I'll talk to-you about how design a printer that can print on windows ten mobile.
So, this is an architecture slide that you may be familiar with if you
follow long printing for the last few years...architectures
largely unchanged a few things to point out we have a print manager
...print dialogue interaction on the left here and that's used to set up
the print job that's how we get all the configuration data to your app ...
we have a number of app rendering api is available depending on what kind
of content use so html five xhtml those are
both very easy but if you have a more advanced app you can certainly use direct
...or on the express print document package target api both of
those are available now new windows ten is.
A mobile support for printing on windows send mobile.
That's that doesn't use any print...so it's a bit different we'll talk about the details of that when
we get into the...
So, comparing windows ten windows send mobile I mention that windows ten mobile does not use print
drivers but
...number of other differences that affect your customers experience
first one windows ten you're already familiar with the fact that supports usb network
shared virtual printers whereas on mobile we only support network printers.
On windows ten we install printers ahead of time whereas on windows ten mobile they're
all installed on-demand we discover that runtime
if there compatible will set them up automatically
supporting printers we support any driver on windows ten
has a driver available so practically any device that's been created whereas on
windows ten we only support printers that support our new windows mobile stack that must support the
devious print protocol and one of our standard plus.
And, then finally on windows ten we support a lot of
apps new windows apps older windows...apps then...apps and all the
...on windows ten mobile only windows apps are able to print so-if you have a
silverlight based windows phone app there's no change in the ability of that to support printing.
So, what printers do we actually support on windows send mobile
answers we've got over nineteen hundred printer supported right now we're working closely
with all the manufactures to develop a more printers will be in the market this fall?
Most popular brands are supported
and we'll be able to release details on that closer general availability of the product and,
as a bonus we've actually added support for saving is a pdf which is
great if you don't happen to have a printer that's new enough to support windows ten mobile but,
you still want to get a recede or something else save to a fixed document.
So, with that I think the most interesting thing to do is actually show
you a demo of what printing from windows ten mobile looks like.
So, I've got an app that I authored here.
Using the new windows apps sdk that works for windows ten and windows
ten mobile.
So, I've got a phone here you can sort of see I've got just
a simple document reader this is using the windows
pf api and if I click the print
button I have you'll notice that we go into a pretty familiar print dialogue
and this printer that that's sitting next to me here was automatically discovered and I can
...options on that if I want I can change the copies or what have you but I'm just going to actually show that
it prints?
...I can find the button
...goes and...preparing the document right now rendering to this hp printer
informant we call pc lambda so momentarily here...paper coming out.
There is so you can see we have paper on the screen that.
Matches what we had on the screen.
All right.
All right with that I'm going to tell you about how we can write apps
that print on windows ten windows more ten mobile.
So, in windows ten we've developed a new version of our app platform
it's built on the windows eight app platform and we're just going is windows apps
the key difference here is you can build the app once and run it everywhere the source that I had on the phone a
...just a minute ago runs both on windows ten windows ten mobile
without any changes I don't have to compile it separately currently
printing support on both windows ten and windows ten mobile but,
we don't support on platforms like xbox and,
we don't support it for legacy windows phone apps.
there have been a couple of minor changes from windows eight-point one apps so-if you have
an app that already works for that platform...a couple things will need to do first we've
remove the charms based print at entry point so every app that supports printing now
needs to have its own print button this is good because it gives you control over when users can access
this experience and make sure that it's actually familiar across all of your different apps so,
the mitigation is just put in a print button and make sure
...the print buttons only visible when it's when it makes sense too and,
then finally the print api is publish for all platforms and what that means is
your app needs to fail gracefully in the event printing is not supported
so if you ran your app on a platform
...printing wasn't supported it's okay nothing will happen you catch the exception?
Okay, with that last time we did a talk
at build we showed how you do printing from
...html five and javascript...and that was great because that's a
very easy experience for people to usehowever,
based on all of our telemetry most app developers are actually writing and csharp an
example the platform there's a little more challenging.
it's actually not as complicated as you think so I wanted to detail that in this in the sample that we're going to
show on-screen today this is not the sample that you will find
on msdn if you were...look in our sample gallery what
...a cut down version of
that really is demonstrated optimize understanding on the
slides there's a much more sophisticated sample available in you should work for from that?
So, what we'll do to start?
Is follow along on the sequence diagram on the right side of the slide and you'll see how the
calls basically flow?
In this phase we're basically just registering a bunch of delegates to
read register for printing so first we register for print
...requested and then we'll show a print button when the user clicks on the print button
we'll call show...and then we'll get a couple of call back so the first
one is the print task requested handler and, then in that event you
actually have to provide a print tasks source requested handler an example what you do there is you
...dot a print document object...provide a reference to that in that method.
You can see the code this is the simplified sample we have so during registering
for printing you see we...print manager we register prefer
protest requested then we build the print document register for all call backs it supports.
After the user clicks print the print task request of an...fired your delegates invoked
and here you can see we...print task we set a title on the
document we can add support for the completed handler if you want to handle that and,
then if we have any custom options that we have say
printing headers putting folders any special layout options that's
...set these up and I'll show you that.
So, if you decided to add app
specific features to your print dialogue this is basically how you do it first we
grab the displayed options from the print task options object.
And, then we go ahead and add.
To the print task option details we add a new
list option and in this case we're using a fit to page features a good example
and rtwo options for that are scale for scaling to fit and crop for crop to fit.
Once we know what we're doing what add the fit feature to
...displayed options and then
...call back for wintry changes happened to that in this way we can make sure that
we have knowledge of when the feature changes we can changer data model to print appropriately.
Next will handle the print tasks source requested call back and this one very simple all you do
is you set the document source that runtime the only challenge here is it's a very
it's a short time-out for this call back so you want to make sure that you have your document
in your document source fully initialized one advance of this call back.
For example, we generally just set that to that...document object but,
if you had a special data model that required something else you're welcome to use anything that
supports the I print documents source interface and you can use
...for example, there.
The next phase of the print api is the print preview phase so,
if we continue from where we're where we left off by now the print dialogue
ish is appearing and it's going to try and gather the print preview.
So,...all the flow...the right you'll see that we get a call
from the print manager to the print document asking for the print
preview page collection and as part of that it'll call pageant to determine which
pages exist.
Print document passes the pageant call through to your
implement implementation of the pageant handler and, then so for each page that's
return by the pageant handler we'll call to get the print preview.
So, in terms of the code all note that I cheated a little bit on this because
packagings actually the most complicated thing you could do in the app that I showed
all content prepackaged it was a pf that I use the pf api to read but,
if you have a...document the needs to be repackage needed there's a lot more to it and we have a
really detailed sample available in the sdk that you can look at to check
that out but if you have a prepackaged needed document so, for example,
if you're printing images or if you're printing something like the
...page all you have to do is...the page count and then move forward if
...page count would change depending on the size of the page or what have you then you would want
to go ahead and process all those options
...the pageant time and this will be called every time the page sizes changed?
Next every time for every page that you have.
You'll get called forget preview page you'll see that all we do is pass in
...to the print api in order to give the page.
The only thing that's tricky here is theget preview page event args actually passes
...a one based page index so just be aware of that if
your data model zero base like it probably is you'll have to adjust accordingly.
And, that's all there is toprint preview now if you're going
to do rendering it's largely the same as print preview except you've already pageant
...the document so you have to worry about doing that again and,
you just need to change your pages to actually match the resolution of the
screen.
Of the paper sorry.
if any custom options exist we will invoke the option change chandler whenever
that's changed otherwise whatever the user clicks printin the print dialogue not to be
confused with your print button the print document receives a make document call.
The print document will then call through to your app for your ad pages handler and,
finally will fire the protest completed event whenever that.
So, earlier I showed how you configure the option.
In the print dialogue when you get changes what happens is you get fired this option changed
event.
And, you can see basically all we're doing is we're looking to see what the option ideas to make sure
that were adjusting the right thing once we do that we can hydrated
...print option details object and we can have a switch based on the
arguments now I didn't detail what exactly
would do in these cases because it's very specific to the data model but the operation and,
the data flow here would be the same regardless of what kind of options...handling.
After the user clicks print obviously we're going to the ad pages call we mentioned
that earlier unlike the get print preview page call
...pages a single call for the entire document.
So, what you want to do is you loop through the pages that we have to add and we add those to the
print document object and,
you're going to want to make sure that you read-out the page description from the print task options?
So, once you have the page resolution you're
going to want to adjust your url element to make sure that it's rendered
...the target resolution you'll see in the example that we have...data model and ask
for copy of the page in the target resolution and, then I pass in an x in
a wide dimension and you'll notice that we use this image of all
...from the page description and,
that's actually given in what we call device independent pixels advice independent
pixels one ninety-six of an inch of convert that to dpi what we're going
...do is convert that divided by in ninety six and then take it times the
dpi for that dimension and...actually have the page resolution that we actually need to use?
Finally when you're done adding pages you call ad pages complete and we're done.
Once you completed printing will fire the print task completed event argument here you'll be able to check
the completion property and figure out how it how it completed there's a chance
...failed the user...it and, this is where you'll find out and it's a good opportunity let the user
no if something went wrong.
So, in this example I just show popping
a message dialogue after the protest completion state certified.
...nutshell that's all it takes to do printing example I know it seems like a lot of steps and
they're a lot of delegates but you saw from this example that none of the none of the methods are
very complicated obviously I mention that pageant...is the hardest part and your data
model might require somewhat heavier lifting than this one did but if you
have a data model the three pageant...say photo viewer
say pf fewer those things make it much easier to do and you should totally
ad printing...example.
With that we've got a call action
so-if you have windows eight or eight point one apps please update those to windows apps
place...print button in the y and then make sure that you catch any
exceptions thrown by show print you icing just in case you're app is running
...a platform that doesn't support parting right now and, we also need your help as,
you know, data models and printing and printers there's a lot of variability that could happen and we
want your help testing so please test on windows ten and windows ten mobile
especially and, report any problems that you find using msdn
forums or the windows feedback app this is going to help us make sure that we have the best experience
...your customers and ours.
And, with that that's all the content that we have for app developers so-if that's why
you're here thank you for tuning in we appreciate it but if you happen design printers as
well please hang out and we'll tell you about how design printers that work well for windows ten windows
and mobile next so-if you're still with us that means you probably
develop printers for windows and windows ten mobile and we'll tell you about all the details that you need to know to
be successful designing those.
First I think it's important to talk about some of the standards that we've added support for...
windows ten we've had support for open xp essence windows eight but,
in windows ten windows...mobile...that
support forward in addition we've added support for to raster formats the first one is called
pg raster it's a format from the printer working group and, that support on both windows ten
windows send mobile and additionally just for windows ten mobile we've added support for
another raster format call pc lm which is developed by the wi-fi alliance.
These investments are going to help low resource printers develop
very easily without needing drivers so we're really excited that we have these supported.
So, mobile windows ten mobile...requirements
...a few things you have to do to make your printer work first you have to support at least one of
our standard communication protocols we will support the existing obvious print implementations that
you have had in addition we also have a new version of w sprint called...
print two-point-zero we'll talk about that did a little later...support at least one of our standard
dls...support for of them ...raster
pcm open xp and we also added support for the existing microsoft xp standard.
Finally you have to support discovery so new devices will need to add support for the
mobile printer category...their ws discovery meta data and then tell us what pl
the support in a database print implementation and then we can also support
some existing devices please contact us if you'd like more information about that since
...a special process that involves engineering effort on our side.
Developing a windows ten mobile supported printer is obviously great if you
want to work on a phone sized device but it also has benefits on the desktop
mobile compatible printers will automatically be support on desktop with
class drivers so you won't have to deliver any
software on windows update on your website to get those devices working all note that
pcm printers still require third-party driver but if you supported
any other formats we will support those and, then if you support w sprint two-point-zero you
can additionally get custom features custom options localized option names
and, then custom bidirectional status and queries?
So, I mention...print two-point-zero a couple of times and what that does it allows printers to
expose custom device features without a driver this is
a really easy protocol the to develop if you already have a...print one-point-zero implementation
...five new operations you can support the first one is prepared to print this
...strictly informative operation that allows a printer to warm-up, for example,
if it has a few...something along those lines that
takes some time to get ready from called start second we have create print job
to which is an extension of the create print job operation that allows you to
...print schema print ticket in order to know what the
customers requested for print job?
Next we have a get print device capabilities operation
which allows retrieval of our new print device capabilities document we have a get
print device resources operation which allows retrieval of
any localize resources using res x and then finally we have the ability to get
...I schema extensions using the get by I scheme extension operation.
So, you might be asking.
What pda elsa implement and they're a lot of choices here open
x ps is obviously a great format because you get full for decked fidelity vector
...rendering the smallest available...
But, parsing can be memory intensive on a printer there's a lot of
functionality is baked into that protocol or the pl that needs to be
dealt with in the device so this is really best for enterprise class devices.
Pg raster on the other hand
has a very low processing overhead so it could be used on practically any printer and,
then page processing intent is built into the pl with a simple page header.
The drawback is the large profile size can cause slower
printing associated with just network traffic.
So, this is really a good choice for injects or low-cost laser devices that don't have a lot of on board ram.
And, then pc...another good choice it's a proper subset of
cdf so it's easy to parse if you already have a cdf engine and,
it uses more compression so the pl
...smaller on the drawback side there's no built-in processing intent and there's no
class driver for windows ten so you'll have to bring your own in general we think this is best for
product lines that already have...support built-in
so medium-size laser devices or high-end laser devices
that don't support open experience so I mention briefly the print device capabilities format as well
I have an example of a snippet of that on the right.
In a nutshell this is just a new
...a document type that we can use to easily generate print capabilities and print ticket.
Include simple constraints...option for...raster consumers so, for example,
you can specify that you want the backside of a...of a
piece of paper tumbledwhen you're printing a duplex document and this is really great because it
allows us to know the mechanics of the device better to generate the right pl for you?
Additionally we support the res...format now to localize your custom
features and options so you can see a simple example of a res x file on the right the
key detail here is the name element is going to be formatted using a
subset of your.
Of your print schema name space so in the example we've given the full print schema name space
for the can tokyo devices that we're using is going to be
schemas dot co dot com twenty fourteen print schema and then the option
name is separated by a slash an and tacked on to the
...called main and then we give the localize value of that in the value
element that's all there is to it is one file per local and windows
...retrieve those from the device using this print two-point-zero one additional tidbit we've put in is
the device can actually redirect to a web service if you have those published
online so it may be best if you keep your additional
...locales online and let us retrieve them that way?
And, that's a good high-level overview of what we have for printer
isv that are developing printers to work on windows ten windows ten mobile
so what we'd like to ask you to do is add support for windows ten mobile
...devices as we describe before you choose one or more standard
...else for your device and build...your printer
adds support for the mobile printer category and...discovery.
Update your ws print implementation to describe the
...the support.
...support for...print two-point-zero
whenever you-get-a-chance this is optional but it gives you a lot more value and then be sure to
test your printer against the hardware lab kit to ensure compatibility we've got a lot of new tests and
there to help you validate your devices against mobile and, if you have trouble please let us know.
Of course if you have existing printers which supporter standards please contact pr
and info at microsoft-dot-com for more information
...how we can include support for your devices and upcoming releases.
For more information we have a number of white
papers and specifications published so,
we have details on supporting printers on windows
...we have the print schema service...specification that allows
you to understand more about the print device capabilities format.
We have the w st print service specification for
...print two-point-zero information on the for driver improvements in windows
...and finally a small...the device profile for web services.
So, thank you for watching.